Guide to the Jomo Joka Omowale Papers, 1969-2008 RL.00975
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jomo Joka Omowale papers
1969-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Omowale, Jomo Joka
RL.00975
25 Linear Feet
Jomo Joka Omowale, born as Cleveland McKinley Davis and also known as Eric Thompson, is a parolee in North Carolina who spent much of his life imprisoned in New York and Virginia. He was a leader of the Attica prison riot in 1971. Collection includes court transcripts, legal papers and correspondence, court documents, photographs, press coverage and clippings, and internal prison policies and procedures from Omowale's many years in various prisons. Cases include armed robbery in Virginia, the Attica riots and subsequent trials, three trials regarding a police shooting in Brooklyn, and a murder of a drug dealer in Virginia. Omowale was convicted in the final case, and his pursuit of parole in Virginia following the elimination of parole in the 1990s is another significant component of the collection. Other materials include prisoner poetry and writings, personal correspondence between Jomo and his family, prisoner poetry, Attica Brothers Legal Defense materials, and court documents regarding a White Panther Party trial in 1970. Also includes hundreds of mugshots from New York. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive (Duke University).
Approximately 18,750 items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Jomo Joka Omowale Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2011.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1942 April 10 Born as son of sharecroppers, Infield, North Carolina. Grew up in Virginia Beach, Virginia.
1961 Married Bobbi Lee Forman. They divorced in 1978.
1961-1963 Jailed for burglary, Princess Ann Jail, Virginia.
1968 Arrested in Virginia for robbery; escaped and went to New York.
1968 Arrested in New York for robbery, sent to Sing Sing Prison.
1970 Transferred to Auburn Prison, New York.
1970-1971 Involved in Black Panther Party in Auburn Prison; transferred to Attica Prison.
1971 September Involved in Attica Prison riots: Controled the "D" Door. Was shot 6 times when police stormed the prison.
1971 Vincent Doyle took over Davis defense in Attica trial and appointed Elizabeth Gaynes as counsel.
1973 Davis accepted "Alfred plea" for time served and was released from New York. He returned to Virginia to complete his sentence there. He then returned to New York to complete his time for his initial sentence, and was paroled in New York.
1975 Governor of New York pardoned Davis for his involvement in the Attica Prison riots.
1976 Married Elizabeth Gaynes.
1978 April 2 Involved in a shooting in Brooklyn, NY, which ended with the death of two police officers and Dalou, an aquaintance of Davis. Davis was also shot. He was arrested for the murders and was severely beaten en route to the hospital, requiring reconstructive surgery on his face. His vision was permanently impaired.
1978-1980 Davis was tried 3 times for the murders of the policemen and Dalou. The first 2 trials ended with hung juries, and he was acquitted the third time and released.
1983 Davis and Gaynes separated. He moved to Virginia Beach, where he was involved (with 2 others) in an attempted robbery of drug dealer Robert Stith. Stith was killed during the robbery. Davis was wounded in the leg. He fled to Washington and then went on to New York.
1984-1985 Davis was a fugitive on the FBI's 10 Most Wanted list. His co-defendents entered guilty pleas.
1985-1986 Davis was captured and tried for murder and robbery. He was sentenced to prison, to be eligible for parole in 10-11 years.
1990s-2007 Repeatedly denied parole under Virginia's law eliminating parole.
2008 Paroled. Moved to North Carolina to live near his children.
Collection Overview
Collection includes legal documentation and court transcripts from Omowale's various trials, including Attica-related trials and the subsequent lawsuits brought by the Attica Brothers. Also represented are court cases from his armed robbery conviction in Virginia Beach; his repeated murder trials in New York regarding police shootings (and his lawsuits against New York following his acquittal from those shootings); and his murder conviction in Virginia in 1985. Also included are many materials from his wife and attorney, Elizabeth Gaynes, particularly regarding his legal defense in those trials as well as her attempts to gain his parole in Virginia in the 1990s and 2000s.
Other materials in the collection include personal correspondence between Omowale and Elizabeth Gaynes, as well as correspondence between him and other family members, in particular his daughter, Emani. Other correspondence exists between him and other Attica Brothers, regarding the Attica trials and the lawsuits that followed. Photographs, particularly of mugshots, are another significant component of the collection. The remainder of the materials are prison writings; publicity and press coverage of Jomo Joka Omowale's many court cases; news clippings about him, parole, and other related topics; and miscellaneous documents collected by Omowale during his time in prison.
Acquired as part of Duke University's Human Rights Archive.
Related Materials
An oral history with Jomo Joka Omowale is available in the Center for Documentary Studies student projects collection, series "Duke Spring 2011", subseries "Introduction to Oral History", file "Jomo. Recordings, images, and documents related to interview with Cleveland "Jomo" Davis." The oral history can be accessed by requesting Digital-materials RL01266-SET-0001, E-folder RL01266-DVD-0002, E-folder Jomo.
Additional materials documenting the Attica prison revolt can be found in the Elizabeth Fink papers, also held in Rubenstein Library's Human Rights Archive.
African American prisoners; Murder -- New York (State) -- New York; Murder -- Virginia; Prison riots -- New York; Trial practice -- New York; Trials (Murder) -- New York (State) -- New York; Trials (Murder) -- Virginia; Trial practice -- Virginia; Transcripts; Photographs; News photographs; Identification photographs; Prisoners of war -- Government policy -- United States; Prisoners -- United States -- Correspondence; Black Panther Party; Davis, Cleveland M.; Attica Correctional Facility; Attica Defense Committee; Omowale, Jomo Joka; Thompson, Eric; Gaynes, Elizabeth
- Attica Prison Riot and Trials, 1969-2001, 7 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes clippings with coverage of Black Panther Party, Attica riots and trials of Attica Brothers, as well as coverage of the lawsuits filed by the Attica Brothers against New York. Includes legal correspondence and documents, proceedings, motions, and orders from the court cases following the Attica riots. Also contains Attica Brothers Legal Defense materials, as well as legal documents from a White Panther Party case from 1970. Finally, includes witness files from the Wade Hearing held in 1975.
  - Black Panther Party clippings, 1969-1975 and undated (Box 1)
  - Attica/Auburn Department of Corrections files, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Court papers: John Sinclair/White Panther Party, 1970, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Attica trial materials, approximately dated 1969-1973, 18 folders
    - Pre-trial correspondence (Box 1)
    - Grand Jury proceedings, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Jury pooling (Box 1)
    - Attica Brothers (Box 1)
    - Indictments (Box 1)
    - Autopsies and lab reports (Box 1)
  - Attica trial, 20 folders (Box 2)
    - Assignment of counsel (Box 2)
    - Attica Brothers Legal Defense (Box 2)
    - Motions regarding venue (Box 2)
    - Trial documents: People of New York vs. Attica Brothers, 1973-1975, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - State of New York vs. Eric Thompson, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Legal papers (Box 2)
  - Attica trial, 21 folders (Box 3)
    - Legal papers, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Inmates' personal property issues (Box 3)
    - Evidence/discovery issues (Box 3)
    - Attica Defense Committee legal papers (Box 3)
    - Jomo's notes on Attica trial, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous petitions, etc. (Box 3)
  - Attica materials, 25 folders (Box 4)
    - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Attica Brothers defense (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous materials (Box 4)
    - News clippings about the case and trials (Box 4)
    - Press releases and coverage (Box 4)
  - Attica materials, 20 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous materials, including post-trial (Box 5)
    - Attica Brothers Legal Defense files (Box 5)
    - Court of claims, 1975-1979 (Box 5)
    - Attica Brothers' lawsuits, including Omowale vs. State of New York (Box 5)
  - Attica materials, 35 folders (Box 6)
    - Lawsuits against Nelson Rockefeller, et al, 1981 (Box 6)
    - Attica Brothers Legal Defense (Box 6)
    - Governor pardons and lawsuit settlement, 1977-2001 (Box 6)
  - Wade Hearing witness files, A-Z (Box 6)
  - Omowale vs. New York, re: Attica, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Attica News issues, May 1974-June 1975 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Attica Prison Calendar, 1974 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Attica memorial book, 1974 (Oversize-folder 1)
- Other Court Cases and Trials, 1971-2008, 4 boxes
  Legal documents, correspondence, and other materials relating to Omowale's non-Attica trials, including his armed robbery conviction in Virginia, his repeated murder trials in New York, and his murder trial in Virginia. Also includes a large amount of material from his quest for parole in Virginia in the 1990s and 2000s.
  - New York trials, re: police shootings, 1978-1980 (Box 7)
    - Coverage and clippings (Box 7)
    - Virginia parole correspondence, 1980 (Box 7)
    - New York vs. Davis legal documents, 1979-1980 (Box 7)
    - Double jeopardy research (Box 7)
  - Davis vs. Supreme Court and Eugene Gold, 1980 (Box 7)
  - Davis and Gaynes vs. State of New York, 1980-1989 (Box 8)
  - Davis and Gaynes vs. Village of Menands, 1979-1985
    - Correspondence, legal documents, etc. (Box 8)
  - Commonwealth of Virginia legal materials
    - Armed robbery warrant correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 8)
    - Parole, 1972-1975 (Box 8)
    - Appeal of conviction, 1987-1988 (Box 8)
    - Habeas Corpus suits (Box 8)
  - Akil Al-Jundi vs. Vincent Mancusi, 1995-2000 (Box 8)
  - Virginia parole case, 1980s-2008 (Box 9)
    - Letters supporting Jomo's case for parole (Box 9)
    - Parole Board decisions (Box 9)
    - Parole research re: Virginia (Box 9)
    - Appeals (Box 9)
  - Virginia parole case, 1980s-2008 (Box 10)
    - Letters supporting Jomo's case for parole (Box 10)
    - Parole Board decisions (Box 10)
    - Parole research re: Virginia (Box 10)
    - Appeals (Box 10)
    - Habeas Corpus case, 1990s (Box 10)
- Correspondence, Personal Papers, and Clippings, 2 boxes
  Includes handwritten correspondence between Jomo Omowale and Elizabeth Gaynes, as well as by Omowale to other family members. The Attica Brothers correspondence largely discusses the trials and condition of the Attica Brothers still in prison. Also included in this series are various poems and writings, both by Omowale and other prisoners, as well as by some of Omowale's supporters. Also included are clippings and press coverage of Omowale and his court cases.
  - Jomo's research and writings and notes on science, politics, race, etc. (Box 8)
  - Poetry, etc., by Emani (Jomo's daughter) (Box 8)
  - Correspondence (Box 11)
    - Attica Brothers, 1970s (Box 11)
    - Jomo's personal correspondence, to Gaynes and Emani (Box 11)
  - Prisoner poetry and writings (Box 11)
  - Press coverage and clippings (Box 11)
- Court Transcripts, 1971-1985, 5 boxes
  Court transcripts from the Attica trials and its Wade Hearing from 1975, as well as other trials both against and brought by Jomo.
  - Wade Hearing re: Attica, 15 January 1975-6 February 1975 (Box 12)
  - Wade Hearing re: Attica, 10 February 1975-11 March 1975 (Box 13)
  - Wade Hearing re: Attica, 12 March 1975-26 March 1975 (Box 14)
  - Commonwealth of Virginia vs. Cleveland M. Davis, Virginia Beach, 18 February 1971 (Box 14)
  - Grand Jury proceedings, 4 May 1972 (Box 14)
  - State of New York vs. Eric Thompson, indictments 5 and 15, 26 June 1973 (Box 14)
  - Attica Brothers vs. Nelson Rockefeller, et al, 29 January 1974-31 January 1974 (Box 14)
  - State of New York vs. John Hill and Charles Pernasalice, 25 February 1974 (Box 15)
  - New York vs. Eric Thompson, indictments 5, 15, 38, 39, 41, 11 March 1974 (Box 15)
  - Attica Brothers vs. Nelson Rockefeller et al, 13 March 1974 (Box 15)
  - Attica Brothers vs. Erie County, etc., 30 April 1974 (Box 15)
  - New York vs. Eric Thompson, indictments 38, 39, 41, 6 May 1974 (Box 15)
  - State of New York vs. Eric Jomo Thompson, 22 May 1974 (Box 15)
  - State of New York vs. Eric Thompson, re: Bill of Particulars, 23 May 1974 (Box 15)
  - State of New York vs. Eric Thompson, re: dismissal, 6 June 1974 (Box 15)
  - Pre-trial conference, Supreme Court, 17 June 1974 (Box 15)
  - Waiver and stipulation proceedings, 23 June 1975 (Box 15)
  - Trial against Thomas Wood, 27 November 1978 (Box 15)
  - Trial against Cleveland Davis, 4 April 1979-24 April 1979, 4 folders (Box 15)
  - Transcript of examination of Cleveland Jomo Davis, 15 February 1985 (Box 15)
  - Commonwealth of Virginia vs. Cleveland Davis, 16 May 1985 and 31 July 1985 (Box 16)
  - Commonwealth of Virginia vs. Cleveland M. Davis, 26 November 1985 (Box 16)
  - Commonwealth of Virginia vs. Cleveland M. Davis, 2 December 1985 (Box 16)
  - Commonwealth of Virginia vs. Cleveland Jomo Davis, 1985? (first pages missing) (Box 16)
  - Commonwealth of Virginia vs. Cleveland M. Davis, 23 December 1985 (Box 16)
- Miscellaneous Files and Materials, 2 boxes; 3 oversize folders
  Miscellaneous materials include correspondence, legal paperwork, fliers, and other materials. The crime scene photographs are extremely gruesome.
  - Legal correspondence re: Virginia Beach armed robbery, 1971-1975 (Box 16)
  - Legal papers re: Jomo vs. Sheriff Joe Smith, 1985 (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous, including personal and legal materials, 11 folders (Box 16)
  - Crime scene photographs, trial unknown (Box 16)
  - Omowale vs. State of New York, claim #59593, 1975 (Box 20)
  - Prison publications and zines, 1970s and undated, 3 folders (Box 20)
    Contains a variety of materials including black community newsletters, articles about the KKK and racial oppression, zines created by prisoners, and handouts and pamphlets about particular convicts.
  - Notes, legal documents from Jomo Davis Defense Committee, 1973-1983 (Box 20)
  - Legal notes, documents, and correspondence, 1973-1980, 6 folders (Box 20)
  - Notes, photographs of a wrecked car (case unknown), 1970s and undated (Box 20)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 20)
  - News clippings, 1975 (Box 20)
  - Press and press releases, 1976-1981, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Oversize silhouette target sheet with several bullet holes, undated (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Photographic prints (probably from Attica), undated (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Posters denouncing New York's drug laws as racist, 1998 (Oversize-folder 2)
- Mugshots, 3 boxes
  Hundreds of black-and-white 3x5 inch mugshots of prisoners, which appear to have been taken from New York prisons. Prisoners are identified and some information is provided on the reverse of the photograph.
  - Mugshots (Box 17-19)